Ohlsdorf, Austria LinkedIn

# Josef Heidegger

+43 699 1967 5868 josef.heidegger@outlook.at

I am an engineering leader with 5 years of experience leading teams in product environments. My focus is people growth, improving value delivery, and engineering culture. I bring a deep passion for software and have a diverse background of business models, having worked for an agency, a small-scale start-up, a SME, and an enterprise. I am at my best when there are a clear vision, an aggressive strategy, and motivated people around me.

# **Work Experience**

#### Fronius International GmbH Manager of Process, Methods & Tools

Jun 2021 - Present

Thalheim bei Wels, Austria Hard & Software Engineering, RnD, BU Solar Energy

Leader and line manager of 2 teams (15-20 ppl) around DevOps and agile in the fastest growing business unit of Fronius.

- Leading and growing a team of >10 Agile Coaches (SMs and RTEs) that coach >15 distributed teams in 3 agile release trains (cloud and IoT, ~200 engineers)
- Refocusing and growing the DevOps (former "Tools") development team around 2 major DevOps platforms –
  configuration & release management, and monitoring & analytics
- Working on decentralization and scaling strategies as part of Hard & Software Engineering's leadership
- Contributed to our highly successful 2022 objective for reducing the lead-time between feature planning and rollout by 50% for all IoT software (the objective workgroup is also led from my team)
- Established nightly build integrations and bi-weekly alpha deliveries of our IoT software bundle
- 2021 core-team member of a company-wide task force workgroup where we established a single source of truth for our feature backlog and an 18-month forecast
- Continuously working on myself by visiting internal and external trainings around leadership, agile and DevOps

#### **EUVIC Software GmbH**

# **Teamlead Software development**

May 2020 - May 2021

Vienna, Austria

**Development Team** 

Line manager of a team of ~10 developers and responsible for modernizing the development and delivery methods as the company was transitioning from a project to a product business model

- Restructured the development team for focus and impact by forming delivery teams around products, introducing elements of Scrum, and hiring two senior developers and one tester
- Introduced practices like CI/CD, code reviews, automated testing, and coached developers to take ownership of the engineering quality
- Better engineering practices resulted in significantly fewer defects and time spent on feedback cycles (~4x) and manual deployments
- Improved the security of the product-platform by managing an external security review/pen-test and overseeing the implementation of the countermeasures for the vulnerabilities
- Met important deadlines for a crucial project via monitoring velocity data and estimating feature delivery times

# **Tablet Solutions GmbH**

#### **Lead Developer**

Nov 2016 - Mar 2020

Vienna, Austria

Product Team (start-up)

Tech Lead of the team behind 'WorkHeld', a cloud-based Industry 4.0 workforce management solution

- Grew the development team from 2 to 6
- Built out practices like CI/CD, automated unit and end to end testing, code reviews, logging and alerting that enabled automated bi-weekly releases and fast response times to defects
- Oversaw two general rewrites of the web app and several major refactoring of the mobile apps that sped up critical user interactions around 200x
- Architecting and lobbied for a product customization strategy around feature toggles that was crucial for scaling in our market

#### **Tablet Solutions GmbH**

### Senior Developer (Mobile, Web)

Aug 2016 - Oct 2016

Vienna, Austria

Product Team (start-up)

Senior Developer contributing to the mobile and web apps for the MVP of 'WorkHeld', a cloud-based Industry 4.0 workforce management solution

- Took over prototypes and successfully finished the MVP version of the product on time to extend our runway
- Began as one of the first two engineers and was promoted to Lead Developer after three months

## The diamond dogs:group/Emakina CEE Software Developer

Jan 2011 - Jul 2016

Vienna

**Development Department** 

- IC for various projects in one of Austria's biggest digital agencies mostly for ASP.NET, WPF and Android
- Co-maintainer of the CI/CD toolchain

## **Eurofunk Kappacher GmbH**

## **Software Developer Intern**

**Summer 2010** 

St. Johann im Pongau, Austria

**Control Room Software** 

• Designed and implemented a surveillance-camera control interface for airport security of major German airports

#### **Skills**

<b>Engineering Practices</b>	DevOps, CI/CD, DDD, BDD, OOP, SOA, SOLID, API Design, Trunk Based Development
Product Development	Agile, Scrum, Kanban, SAFe, SaaS products, release management, requirements engineering, configuration management, team topologies, Jira/Confluence
People & Leadership	Coaching, mentoring, sponsorship, hiring, distributed teams, situational leadership, 1-1s
Soft Skills	Calm personality, empathic, approachable & helpful, sense of humor

## Languages

German Native (C2)
English Proficient (C1)
French Basic (A1)

## **Education and Certifications**

•	Certified SAFe® 5 Agilist, Scaled Agile, Inc.	2021
•	Certified Scrum Master, Agile Alliance	2018

Software Engineering, University of Applied Sciences Upper Austria, Hagenberg (no degree)
 BG/BRG Gmunden
 2006 - 2010
 1997 - 2005

# Personal

In my spare time I really like to read, enjoy nature, get lessons from history, and spend time with my family. I also get myself excited over team-sports and try to find new personal challenges with mountain biking.